Guide to the Provost Charles Peake Administrative Records, 1967-1971 UA.3.1.1
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Provost Charles Peake Administrative Records
1967-1971
ULS Archives & Special Collections
University of Pittsburgh. Office of the Provost
UA.3.1.1
16.38 Linear Feet (39 boxes)
Dr. Charles Peake (1906-1993) served as the first Provost of the University of Pittsburgh from 1968 to 1971. These records contain a large amount of material, such as correspondence and reports, relating to the administration of academic and research units and developments at the university and its branch campuses.
Biography
Dr. Charles Peake (1906-1993) served as the first Provost of the University of Pittsburgh from 1968 to 1971. During his time as Provost, the English Language Institute was established; the Departments of Philosophy and Physics were strengthened; and the Schenley Hotel was purchased and converted into a student union. After retirement from his position as Provost, Peake served as an adviser for the Vice Chancellor of Chinese University in Hong Kong.
Peake was from Medina, Ohio, and earned his Bachelor of Arts, Master of Arts, and doctoral degrees all from the University of Michigan. He was married to Margo Carroll and had one daughter, Terry Anne. In 1942, he enlisted in the U.S. Army and served until the end of World War II in areas throughout the United States and in New Guinea. After his military service, Peake became the Assistant Dean of the College of Literature, Science and the Arts at the University of Michigan. Peake eventually left Michigan and rose to become the Dean of the College at Knox College from 1950 to 1956. From Knox College, Peake accepted the position of Assistant Chancellor of Student Affairs at the University of Pittsburgh.
As Assistant Chancellor of Student Affairs, Peake is credited with creating new offices and programs such as the Admission Office, the Scholarship and Student Aid Office, the University Counseling Center, and the Student Employment Office, among others. In fall 1959, Peake became the Vice Chancellor of Academic Disciplines, the School of Liberal Arts and the School of General Studies. In 1967, Peake was promoted to Acting Provost in charge of all the educational and research entities except those in the Health Professions. From there, Peake was appointed the first Provost of the University on May 15, 1968.
Scope and Content Notes
The records of the University of Pittsburgh's first Provost, Dr. Charles Peake, contain a large amount of material relating to the administration of academic and research units and developments at the university and its branch campuses. Of note are documents relating to the division of the Modern Languages Department into the departments of Romantic Languages, Germanic Languages and Literature, Slavic Languages and Literature, and the Chinese Language and Area Center; a cooperative program with Hong Kong University; the debate over the continued presence of the Reserve Officer Training Corps on campus; and efforts to diversify the faculty and student body. The files in this collection are arranged alphabetically by the folder title designated by Provost's office staff.
Related Materials
Chancellor of the University of Pittsburgh, Wesley W. Posvar, Administrative Files, 1967-1991, UA.2.10.1967-1991, University Archives, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Universities and colleges -- Administration -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Universities and colleges -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Records and correspondence; College administrators; Correspondence; Administrative records; University of Pittsburgh. Office of the Provost; Peake, Charles H., 1906-1993
- ACE Academic Intern Program, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Admissions Office, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Content Notes
  Statement by Director of Admissions directed to student applicant; proposed policy statement on admissions and reactions, 1965; creation of Dean of Admissions news release, February 25, 1966; appointment of B. Kobosky as Director, Admissions, news release, June 25, 1966; 100% increase in freshman applications news release, February 16, 1967; list of departments and programs under Provost; correspondence on admissions to college with advanced standing, 1969.
- Advanced Degrees for Faculty, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Proposed policy for eligibility of associated professors for advanced degree, 1970.
- American Association of University Professors, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Meeting notices, newsletter, report; report on projected impact of the draft on the university, 1968.
- Annual Reports, 1967, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Correspondence and reports for various departments used for chancellor's annual reports including University Press and regional campuses.
- Anthropology Department, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Memo on space crisis in Anthropology, 1966; Progress report on journal Ethnology, 1968; proposal for NSF facilities grant, 1968; letter from department chairman on resigning; Report to NSF on cross-cultural cumulative coding center, 1969; Revised proposal to NSF for facilities grant, 1969; letter appointing new department chairman, 1969; minutes of faculty meeting, September 8, 1969; list of books donated to library by Professor Gillen; NSF proposal denied by NSF, November 1969; 5 year development plan for department, 1968.
- Anthropology Department (Div. Social Sciences) (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Anthropology Department (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Anthropology Department-Cornell, American Ethnological Society (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Arts and Sciences proposed graduate school, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Drafts and meeting notes about the proposed graduate school.
- Arts - Future of the Arts, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Statement on teaching applied arts; arts center proposal; Establishing Committee on future of the arts, Curtis Canfield, chairman, 1969; minutes, 1969; related correspondence; Reprint: The University and the Creative Arts; proposed curriculum.
- Arts - Future of the Arts, 1967-1970 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Report of Chancellor's Committee on Future of the Arts, 1970; one clear draft copy, one draft copy with changes.
- Asian Studies, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Draft of Japanese Studies Program, 1967.
- Asian Studies, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Correspondence on the Council on Asian Studies; correspondence about the Asian Studies Program; planning document for Asian studies, 1967; Report of Committee on Asian Studies, 1966-1967; news release and announcements of cultural events relating to Asian Studies Program.
- Astronomy (Div. of Natural Sciences) - Allegheny Observatory (Box 2, Folder 4)
- "B" General File (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Miscellaneous correspondence; Report of Brown University's Advisory Committee on Student Conduct, 1967; paper on Campus Ministry; correspondence with John Birmingham, (Christina Publishing Co.) on gifts to the University.
- Biology Department, Operational Memos, 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Biological Sciences (Div. of Natural Sciences), Reorganization (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Biological Sciences - Special File (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Biophysics - Microbiology, 1967-1969 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Departments of Biophysics and Microbiology merged in 1967; letter from Dr. Lauffer on problems in biological sciences, 1968; correspondence on appointment of department chairman; miscellaneous correspondence.
- Biophysics and Microbiology (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Black Education, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Psychology department program, 1968; correspondence on university-community interaction; memos on Black student standards and accreditation; data on minority students, Fall 1968; School of Education proposals, 1969; proposal on establishment of black history/cultural learning centers, 1968.
- Black Studies Budget and Expenses, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Black Interest Courses, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Correspondence and description on proposed "Black Society and the Law" course in History Department. "Afro American History"; School of General Studies "History and Culture of Black Peoples", extension course in Community Centers; descriptions of Black Studies courses; proposed research projects.
- Black Studies Department Proposal, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  Black Paper on Black Studies prepared by Dr. Jack Daniel and Curtis Porter on behalf of Black Action Society; correspondence on setting up Black Studies program, 1968-1969.
- Black Programs - Finances, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Black Programs - Project A, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  Policy papers and correspondence about Project A under Ford Foundation grant.
- Black Programs - Malcom-Martin-Marcus Program, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  Successor to Project A – policy papers and correspondence.
- Black Programs (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Correspondence on special programs for African Americans, community involvement, racial crisis, and Black Action Society demands.
- Black Programs, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Correspondence on Black Action Society; student programs; plan for extending medical and dental school program by Urban League Health Committee, 1968.
- Black Studies - Administration, 1968-1970 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Correspondence about setting up department, recruiting faculty, courses, space, library support, and scope of department; financial aid for black graduate students; proposal for Martin Luther King Scholarship Fund.
- Black Studies Articles, 1967-1970 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Bradford Campus, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Statement of Revenues and Expenditures, 1969-1970; questionnaire from students in Psychology class on views of trustees relating to University affairs, 1970; correspondence on buying airstrip on campus, 1970; invitation and guest list of chancellor's dinner at Bradford, 1969; correspondence on model cities program at Bradford; correspondence about advisory board; correspondence on operations, 1969-1970.
- Bradford Campus, 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  Statement of operations, January 1967; memos on expansion of campus; description of Freshman English courses at Bradford; Report on college journalism by a campus newspaper; paper on long term objectives for Bradford campus; policy guidelines; rough map of proposed campus.
- Budget Submission Memos, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Business, Graduate School, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  Correspondence on development of the school; correspondence on school administration; Dean's 6-month progress report to Chancellor, March 1969; Report on how Business School can help black community; news release on lectures, courses, and appointments.
- Business, Graduate School - Publications, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  "The Challenge of the Urbanized World" Marshall Alan Robinson Lecture, July 1969; Management Research Center's Reports: Organizational Description, 1st Annual Report to Ford Foundation, views on computer operations, 5th. Annual report to office of Naval Research.
- Business, Graduate School - Perloff, 1968-1969 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  Correspondence about Dr. Robert Perloff, head of Management Research Bureau.
- Business, Graduate School - Albert Wesley Frey Chair of Marketing, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Business, Graduate School, January-June 1968 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  Guidelines on international dimensions; memos on need for expansion funds; recommendations on candidates for deanship; memos on business/engineering major; notice about Marshall Alan Robinson Award; memos on school administration; report and memos on Board of Viewers; Annual report 1967-1968.
- Business, Graduate School, July-December 1968 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  List of members on advisory board for career development courses in General Studies; correspondence about Alumni newsletter; memos on cooperation with Economics Department; memos on organizational structure; speech on future of Business School given by Dr. Zoffer; remarks on assuming deanship; memos to chancellor on future of the school; memos on school administration.
- "C" General File, 1966-1970 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  News release and clippings on merger of Carnegie Institute of Technology and Mellon Institute (Carnegie-Mellon University), 1966; correspondence on National Advisory Committee on Civil Disorders; proposal for Citizenship Information Center, 1970.
- Cabinet Meetings (University), 1969 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  Includes memo on cabinet reorganization, April 15, 1969; Chancellor's staff meeting, October 22, 1969 includes memo on changing cabinet to Chancellor's staff meeting; staff meeting minutes, October 22-November 19, 1969.
- Carnegie Museum, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  Papers on connection between Pitt and Carnegie Museum, particularly with Earth and Planetary Sciences Department.
- Chancellor, 1967-1970 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  Correspondence about Search Committee for Dean, Social Work's "Super high schools plan;" Posvar speech "University and City" at N.E.E.D. dinner, 1967; memo on reorganization of administration, 1967; news release and clippings on Litchfield; Chancellor's planning document, 1968; miscellaneous memos from chancellor.
- Chancellor - Minutes of University Cabinet Meetings, July 18, 1967-June 26, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Chancellor-Staff Meetings, July 1, 1968-March 26, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Chemical Information Center, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  Proposal to National Science Foundation for Chemical Information Center and accompanying memos.
- Chemistry Department, 1967-1970 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  Chemical Information Center Report to NSF, 1969; correspondence about the administration of department; faculty honors, appointments, and leaves; on new building; proposed program for forensic chemistry.
- Chemistry Department (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Classics Department, 1967-1969 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  Correspondence about faculty and the Marshall Fund Committee.
- Classics Department (Box 6, Folder 6)
- College of Arts and Sciences, 1967-1969 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  List of files transferred to Dean FAS files; proposals for improvement of use of Graduate students in undergraduate instruction, 1967; admissions survey; Study prospectus for a Messiah College Urban Center or College, 1967; memos on registration problems; test results of college level exams for Pitt students; memos on courses; letter from Cresap, McCormick and Paget on transfers from Community Colleges; copy of unofficial student protest publications; descriptions of student cabinet, CAS; memo on self designed major, 1968; college program themes for spring/summer 1969; memo on new course in human sexuality, 1969; procedure for calling meeting of student body; paper "The Mood on Campus," May 28, 1969; paper and memos on professional opportunity program; proposal for Doctor of Arts Degree; out of classroom learning experience proposal; need for more advisors; memo on credit requirements; "A critique of the Grading System…" paper by student Kenneth Schuler.
- College of Arts and Sciences - Undergraduate Council Meeting Minutes, September 1968-December 1969 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- College of Arts and Sciences, Dean's Office, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  Appointment of J. Schneewind as dean, CAS, 1969; news release and clippings; News release and letter about associate dean Dunkelberger receiving chemistry award; letter on attraction of funds to academic departments, 1969.
- Commencement, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  Script from May 29, 1969, Schools of Law and Health Professions; instructions for Marshall's regular commencement April 27, presentation of Choh-Ming Li for honorary degree; Responsibility for special events memo; miscellaneous memos.
- Community College, 1966-1970 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  Reprint from NY Times about the 2 year college; correspondence on transferring Community College students to 4 year college/university and studies on enrollment projections, 1970; correspondence with president of Butler County Community College with program descriptions, 1966; description of Pitt Midday Lecture.
- Community Institutes, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  Correspondence and report "Community Institutes: An Educational alternative for the black community" by Philip McKain, 1970.
- Comparative Communism Program, 1966-1969 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  Proposal to Carnegie Corp., 1966 for inter-university program; report to Carnegie Corp., 1968; Report to Carnegie, 1969; Draft proposal on Cooperative Study of Communist Societies, 1966; Memoranda, 1966-1967.
- Computer Center, 1968-1969 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  Report of survey of computer usage by Crystallographers in educational institutions; notice of creation of Senate Committee on computer usage, 1968; NSF Proposal for "A Regional Experiment in Computing in a secondary school system"; Professor Borkowski inventing new lunar language; miscellaneous correspondence; Report, "A Criticism of Computing Center Policies and operation by Physical Sciences users," October 13, 1969.
- Computer Science Department (Box 7, Folder 6)
  Philosophy on computing activity, 1967; request to IBM for fellowships; Report on advanced research projects Agency Contract, 1966; Computer Center's user committee questionnaire; report of Senate Computer Committee to Senate Council, 1969.
- Computer Science Department (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Computer Science Department - Biomedical NIH grant (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Continuing Education for Women, 1964-1968 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Council of Graduate Schools in U.S., 1968-1969 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  Newsletters; speeches from 1968 Annual Conference; miscellaneous correspondence; correspondence on American Council on Higher Education Bulletins.
- Counseling Center, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  Proposed career information center, 1967; proposal for "creating new college of Human Development" by Warren Hill, Counseling Director; description of counseling activities; talk by C. H. Peake on his position on counseling system.
- Crystallography Department, 1963-1968 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  Approval to make Crystallography lab into a department; complaint by Crystallography department chairman about the Computer Center; departmental memos.
- Crystallography (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Cultural and Educational Exchange, 1968-1970 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  Procedure for waiver of 2 year foreign residency requirement, 1970; moratorium on foreign student admissions, 1969; Reorganization of foreign student office, 1968-1970; problems with foreign admissions and suspensions.
- Culturally Disadvantaged Program, 1968-1970 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  Meeting minutes of study group for program for culturally deprived students, 1967-1968; Resolution of Senate Council, 1968; related correspondence; freshman support program; Ford grant; recruitment efforts; Black Action Society demands for recruitment, admission, faculty appointments; clippings on minority problems.
- Curriculum Revisions, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  College of Arts and Sciences suggested changes in curriculum; proposed course in man-environment; letter from student criticizing grading practices and replies.
- Deans/Provost Meetings, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  Minutes of meetings with accompanying papers; Divisional library plan, statistics on alumni giving, February 2, 1968; Prospectus on Division of Instructional Experimentation, July 2, 1968; procedures for appointment to graduate faculty; suggested organization and procedures for federal grants; U-CEP Coordinating Committee; memo on organization for urban and environmental studies.
- Deans/Provost Meetings, 1969-1970 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  Minutes plus accompanying papers; Undergraduate Council recommendations on out of classroom learning experiences and physical education requirement, February 13, 1969; tenure policy, April 18, 1969; report on student housing, September 8, 1969; professional opportunity program, September 11, 1969; memo on U-CEP activities and goals, September 1969; Report on proposed expansion of advanced industrial societies program, March 24, 1970.
- Draft Law Change, 1967-1968 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  Description of new law; advisory from American Council on Education, July 4, 1967; Student draft questionnaire and replies; memos from deans on impact of draft law; Chancellor's letter to Senator Edward Kennedy on draft, December 22, 1967; letter to Congressmen on Senator Kennedy's amendment to law; notice to students on draft, counseling manuals, 1968; policy on student withdrawal because of draft; memo on graduate student draft studies.
- Earth and Planetary Sciences, 1968-1970 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  Memo on cooperative program with Carnegie Institute of Technology, 1963; proposed fundraising program for department, 1964; review of department and program, 1968; report on department development, 1969; correspondence on department administration; news releases.
- Earth and Planetary Sciences (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Earth and Planetary Sciences (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Earth and Planetary Sciences (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Earth and Planetary Sciences (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Earth and Planetary Sciences - Gulf Oil Co. (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Earth and Planetary Sciences - Pitt-Carnegie Tech Cooperative Program (Box 9, Folder 4)
- East Asian Department, 1968-1969 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  Memos concerning courses and faculty appointments; Paper on Development of East Asian Program, 1968; technical report for East Asian Language and area center, 1968-1969.
- East Asian Languages and Literature (Box 9, Folder 6)
- East Asian Languages Center (Box 9, Folder 7)
  NDEA proposal for Center, 1968; letters to Congress to support language centers; proposal for teaching Chinese, inter-university context; proposal for summer institute; report on center, 1967-1968; related correspondence.
- East Asian Library, 1961-1969 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  Correspondence on needs of East Asian Library; annual report, 1968; holding list of microfilms; Guide to use of Library; report on library by Eugene Wu of Harvard University, 1969.
- East West Center (University of Hawaii), 1967 (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Economics Department, 1967-1970 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  Memos on department affairs 1967-1970; copy of research grant proposal "University – Community Cooperative Manpower research training program" and related correspondence, 1969.
- Economics Department (Box 9, Folder 11)
- Economics Department (Box 9, Folder 12)
- Economics Department (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Economics Department (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Economics Department - Center for Regional Economic Studies (CRES) (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Economics Department - CRES (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Economics Department - CRES including Regional Advisory Committee (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Economics Library Selections Project (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Education, School of, 1969-1970 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  Memos and reports relating to the School of Education; proposed advanced study program for older faculty in Black institutions, 1969; Circular Innovations in School of Education, 1970; Admissions policy for Education Communications, 1970; Questions on admissions in elementary education, 1970; Review of Art Education Program, 1969-1970; Report of School of Education Committee on ROTC program, 1970.
- Ecuador Project Conclusion, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Education, School of International Development Education Program (IDEP), 1968 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  Brochure on IDEP program, 1968; news release on Dr. Spaulding being named head; correspondence about the program.
- Education, School of Higher Education, 1968-1969 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  Middle State Association Document on Higher Education, 1957-1967; Penn State development program for graduate assistants, 1968; Pitt proposal for training university personnel, 1968; Resumé of Alex Ducanis; proposal to HEW Office of Education to train teachers for Community Colleges; proposal for an Institute for Higher Education, 1969.
- Education - Department of Higher Education, 1969-1970 (Box 11, Folder 2)